今晚
Tonight
我们一起走进小川糸的《山茶的
let's step together into Ito Ogawa's The Camellia
情书》
Love Letter.
请把灯光调暗一点
Please dim the lights a little.
把手机放远一点
Set your phone a little farther away.
也许窗外有车声
Maybe there are cars passing outside the window.
也许房间里只有你自己的呼吸
Maybe the only sound in the room is your own breathing.
没有关系
That's all right.
这本书适合在这样的时刻打开
This is a book meant to be opened at moments like this.
它不是一部急着把人推向高潮的
It is not the kind of story that rushes you toward a climax.
故事
story
而像一封慢慢写成的信
but more like a letter slowly written over time.
纸张柔软
The paper is soft.
墨迹微湿
The ink is still slightly wet.
信里有镰仓的风
In the letter, there is the wind of Kamakura.
有旧屋的寒意
There is the chill of an old house.
有孩子长大的背影
There is the retreating figure of a child growing up.
也有一个人重新学习与自己相处
And there is the long process of someone learning again how to live with themselves.
的漫长过程
the long process
《山茶的情书》延续了山茶文具
The Camellia Love Letter continues the world of the Camellia Stationery Shop.
店的世界
The world of the shop
主人公雨宫鸠子
The protagonist, Hatoko Amemiya,
继承了祖母留下的文具店
inherited the stationery store her grandmother left behind
也继承了代笔屋的工作
and also inherited the work of being a letter writer.
她替别人写信
She writes letters for other people,
写道歉
letters of apology,
写祝福
letters of blessing,
写诀别
letters of farewell,
写那些当事人明明放在心里
writing the words the people involved clearly keep in their hearts
却怎么也说不出口的话
but somehow can never say out loud.
写信这件事
Writing letters
在她手里并不只是把词句排列整
in her hands, is not just arranging words and sentences
齐
neatly.
而是替一个人的心找到最恰当的
It is finding the most fitting
姿势
posture for a person's heart.
可是
But
到了这一部里
in this installment,
鸠子的生活已经不再只是文具店
Hatoko's life is no longer just the stationery store,
、信纸和墨水
letter paper, and ink.
她有了丈夫蜜朗
She now has a husband, Mitsuro.
有了长女阳菜
She now had her eldest daughter, Hina,
也就是大家熟悉的QP妹妹
better known to everyone as little QP,
还有两个年幼的孩子小梅和莲太
as well as two younger children, Koume and Renta,
朗
and Akira.
她从一个独自守店的年轻女人
From a young woman minding the shop on her own,
变成了五口之家的母亲
she had become the mother of a family of five.
她仍然爱文字
She still loved words,
爱代笔
loved writing letters for others,
爱那些纸上微小而郑重的仪式
and loved those small, solemn rituals on paper.
可现实生活已经把她卷进了更细
But real life had swept her into an even finer,
碎也更真实的漩涡里
more fragmented, and more authentic whirlpool.
故事开始时
At the start of the story,
鸠子写了一封通知信
Hatoko writes a notice,
告诉曾经关照山茶文具店的人们
telling the people who had once looked after the Camellia Stationery Shop
代笔屋即将重新营业
that the letter-writing service is about to reopen.
信里说
In the letter, she says
樱花又到了盛放的季节
that the cherry blossoms are once again in full bloom,
段葛的维修工程已经告一段落
that the repair work on Dankazura has come to an end,
镰仓的春天正在一点点亮起来
and that spring in Kamakura is brightening little by little.
她也向大家报告家中的新成员
She also tells everyone about the new members of her family.
小梅和莲太朗都已经开始上小学
Koume and Rentaro have both started elementary school
长女阳菜也升入初三
and her eldest daughter, Hina, has moved up to her third year of junior high.
她说这几年因为怀孕、生产、育
She says that over the past few years, with pregnancy, childbirth, and child-
儿
rearing,
生活每天都像太空旅行
each day has felt like space travel:
忙乱、失重、难以掌控
hectic, weightless, and hard to control.
也因此疏于代笔业务
As a result, she has neglected her letter-writing business
给大家添了不便
and caused inconvenience to everyone.
她认真地表达歉意
She offers a sincere apology,
也带着一点重新出发的期待
while also expressing a little hope for a fresh start.
邀请大家在需要的时候
She invites everyone, whenever they need to,
再次来到山茶文具店
to visit Tsubaki Stationery Store once again.
这样一封信
This letter
表面上是营业通知
appears on the surface to be a business notice,
其实更像鸠子写给过去的自己和
but in truth feels more like Hatoko writing back to her past self
旧日时光的一封回信
and to the days gone by.
她终于从一段漫长的育儿假期里
At last, after a long childcare leave,
抬起头来
she lifts her head
看见樱花
and sees the cherry blossoms
看见店门
and sees the shop door
看见那个曾经坐在桌前铺开信纸
She saw the person she used to be, sitting at the desk and spreading out stationery
的自己
before her
可是
But
重新开始并不等于一切恢复原状
starting over doesn't mean everything goes back to the way it was
人一旦走过某些岁月
Once you have lived through certain years
就不可能真的回到从前
you can never truly return to the past
鸠子也明白
Hatoko understood that too
过去那个独自生活、和芭芭拉夫
The person she had been, living alone, keeping company with Mrs. Barbara
人来往、把一天安排得井井有条
and arranging each day in perfect order
的自己
that version of herself
已经远去了
had already receded into the distance
现在的她身边有孩子
Now she had children around her
有家务
housework
有升学
school entrance exams
有青春期的女儿
a teenage daughter
有夫妻之间不必说破却时时存在
and the ever-present, unspoken distance
的距离
between husband and wife
她想回到代笔屋
She wanted to return to the Letter Writing Shop
想找回文字带给她的秩序感
wanted to recover the sense of order that words had given her
可她必须带着现在的全部生活一
but she had to bring the whole of her present life along with her
起回去
Go back
书里的时间顺着四季往前走
In the book, time moves forward with the seasons.
春天过去
Spring passes.
夏天到来
Summer arrives.
又在一支线香花火落地时轻轻结
And then, as a sparkler’s flame drops to the ground, it gently comes to an end.
束
End.
那个夜晚
That night,
鸠子和蜜朗一起在院子里放烟火
Hatoko and Mitsuro set off fireworks together in the yard.
线香花火最后一束火花落在地面
The last shower of sparks from the sparkler falls to the ground.
余烬扑哧扑哧地跳动
The embers sputter and dance,
像一只小动物
like a tiny animal,
随后慢慢被夜色吞没
then are slowly swallowed by the night.
鸠子说
Hatoko says,
结束了呢
It’s over, isn’t it?
她没有说结束的是夏天
She doesn’t say that what is over is summer.
可蜜朗懂
But Mitsuro understands.
两个人之间有一种经过岁月沉淀
Between the two of them is a kind of understanding, settled over many years,
后的默契
a quiet rapport.
句子不必完整
The sentence need not be complete.
意思已经抵达
The meaning has already arrived.
可是
But
当他们拎着水桶回到家
when they got home carrying the buckets
阳菜正一边看电视一边玩手机
Hina was watching TV while playing on her phone
对母亲的招呼没有回应
and didn’t respond when her mother greeted her
青春期的孩子就像一扇半掩的门
A child in adolescence is like a door left half-closed
明明还在同一个家里
Though they are still living under the same roof
却让父母突然不知道该怎样靠近
parents suddenly find themselves unsure how to approach them
鸠子想趁两个小的外宿
Hatoko wanted to take advantage of the two younger ones being away overnight
和阳菜好好单独聊一聊
to have a proper one-on-one talk with Hina
甚至连烟火原本也是为她准备的
Even the fireworks had originally been prepared for her
可阳菜不来
But Hina wouldn’t come
或者说
or rather
她已经不愿意像小时候那样
she was no longer willing, the way she had been as a child
把兴奋、依赖和柔软全都摊开在
to lay all her excitement, dependence, and tenderness out
母亲面前
in front of her mother
去年夏天还几乎每天都想放烟花
Just last summer, she was a child who wanted to set off fireworks almost every day
的孩子
that child
如今沉默地坐在电视前
now sat silently in front of the TV
鸠子只能若无其事地问
Hatoko could only ask, as if nothing were wrong
要吃西瓜吗
Want some watermelon?
阳菜回答
Hina answers,
不吃
I'm not eating.
至少她还愿意回答
At least she's still willing to answer.
这个细节很轻
This detail is subtle,
却很痛
but it hurts.
它不是激烈的冲突
It's not a fierce conflict,
而是亲子关系里最常见也最难承
but the most common and hardest-to-bear change
受的变化
in a parent-child relationship.
孩子并没有离家
The child hasn't left home,
也没有说讨厌你
nor has she said she hates you.
可她正在把自己的世界一点点关
But she is closing off her own world, bit by bit,
起来
shutting it away.
母亲站在门外
Her mother stands outside the door,
既想敲门
wanting to knock,
又怕敲得太响
yet afraid of knocking too loudly.
于是鸠子在心里反复默念
So Hatoko repeats to herself, over and over,
时间是最好的良药
Time is the best medicine.
她知道
She knows
有些阶段不能硬闯
some phases can't be forced through.
只能等待
All you can do is wait.
等待孩子长大
waiting for the child to grow up
等待自己学会放手
waiting for herself to learn to let go
也等待彼此重新找到可以说话的
and waiting for them both to find again
位置
a place where they can talk
小川糸写家庭生活时
When Ito Ogawa writes about family life,
总是有这样的克制
there is always this kind of restraint.
她不把痛苦放大成戏剧
She doesn't magnify pain into drama,
也不急着给关系一个圆满答案
nor does she rush to give a relationship a perfect answer.
她只是让我们看见
She simply lets us see
一个母亲怎样在厨房、客厅、夜
how a mother, amid the smells of the kitchen, the living room, and the night
晚的烟火味里
air tinged with smoke and cooking,
慢慢接受孩子的远离
slowly accepts her child's moving away.
到了冬天
When winter arrives,
故事里出现了热红酒
mulled wine appears in the story.
鸠子在美容院的旅游杂志上读到
Hatoko reads in a travel magazine at the beauty salon
德国人在圣诞前后饮热红酒
that Germans drink mulled wine around Christmas.
于是回家试着做
So she goes home and tries making it.
她把红酒倒进小锅
She pours red wine into a small pot,
加入肉桂、丁香、八角和蜂蜜
adds cinnamon, cloves, star anise, and honey,
有时还放进切成圆片的橘子和苹
and sometimes slices in rounds of orange and apple.
果
As it turned out,
山茶文具店所在的老房子从上一
the old house that housed the Camellia Stationery Shop had been
代传下来
passed down from the previous generation.
修修补补还能住
With patching and repairs, it was still livable,
可一到冬天就特别冷
but once winter came, it grew terribly cold.
热红酒给她的身体带来温暖
The mulled wine warmed her body
也给她一点独属于自己的松弛
and gave her a little ease that belonged only to her.
分娩和育儿之后
Since giving birth and raising the children,
她已经很久没有好好喝酒
it had been a long time since she had really enjoyed a drink.
如今两个小的渐渐能照顾自己
Now that the two younger ones could gradually look after themselves,
她终于重新拥有睡前的一小段时
she finally had a small stretch of time before bed
间
to herself.
酒意让脚步轻飘
The wine made her steps feel light
也让心情舒展
and her mood open up.
她可以暂时忘掉烦恼
For a while, she could forget her worries
沉进自己的世界
and sink into her own world.
如果困意袭来
If sleepiness came over her,
就不等蜜朗回家
she would not wait for Mitsuro to come home;
直接钻进被窝
she would slip straight under the covers.
这里的酒并不是放纵
The drinking here was not indulgence.
而像一个疲惫的人给自己的小小
but like a small bit of permission a weary person gives herself
许可
permission
它说
It says,
你今天已经做得够多了
You've done enough today.
你可以暖一暖
You can warm yourself up a little,
可以停一停
you can pause for a while,
可以不再立刻回应所有人的需求
and you don't have to respond at once to everyone else's needs anymore.
对于长期被家庭事务包围的人来
For someone long surrounded by family affairs,
说
such moments
这样的片刻极其珍贵
are incredibly precious.
鸠子怀念独自生活时的轻盈
Hatoko misses the lightness of living alone.
并不是不爱现在的家
It's not that she doesn't love the family she has now,
而是人在承担许多身份之后
but after taking on so many roles,
依然需要一个不被任何角色占用
a person still needs a corner
的角落
that isn't claimed by any role.
妻子、母亲、店主、代笔人
Wife, mother, shop owner, ghostwriter—
这些身份都是真实的
all of these identities are real.
可在这些名字之外
But beyond those names,
她也只是鸠子
she is also simply Hatoko.
她需要听见自己的声音
She needs to hear her own voice.
哪怕那声音很小
No matter how small that voice may be
像热红酒蒸汽里一点甜而辛香的
like something sweet and spicy in the steam of hot mulled wine
气味
a scent
书名叫《山茶的情书》
The book is titled Camellia’s Love Letter
情书当然是重要的
Of course, love letters matter
可是这里的情书
but the love letters here
并不只属于年轻恋人
do not belong only to young lovers
它也属于逝去的人
they also belong to those who have passed away
属于错过的人
to those who missed their chance
属于无法再当面解释的关系
to relationships that can no longer be explained face to face
属于那些已经沉默多年
to feelings that have been silent for years
却仍然在心里发光的感情
yet still glow in the heart
鸠子接到一项特殊的委托
Hatoko receives a special commission
与上代
connected to Jodai
也就是她的祖母有关
that is, her grandmother
上代在鸠子的生命里
In Hatoko’s life, Jodai
是严厉的、深刻的
was a stern and deeply formative presence
也是难以轻易和解的存在
and someone with whom reconciliation did not come easily
她曾经教鸠子写字、写信
She once taught Hatoko how to write characters and letters
教她作为代笔人应有的规矩与分
and taught her the rules and propriety expected of a scribe
寸
An inch
可祖母的爱常常包裹在严厉之中
But her grandmother's love was often wrapped in sternness
让年少的鸠子感到压抑甚至受伤
making young Hatoko feel stifled, even hurt
祖母去世之后
After her grandmother passed away
鸠子继承了她留下的文具店
Hatoko inherited the stationery shop she left behind
也在漫长的日子里一点点理解她
and over the long days, came to understand her little by little
理解不等于遗忘伤痛
Understanding doesn't mean forgetting the pain
而是终于能看见
but finally being able to see
一个人也许笨拙
that a person may be clumsy
也许不善表达
may be poor at expressing themselves
却仍然用自己的方式爱着
yet still love in their own way
与上代有关的情书
The love letters connected to the previous generation
让鸠子再次面对祖母隐藏在岁月
make Hatoko face once more another side of her grandmother
背后的另一面
hidden behind the years
原来上代也曾有过炽热而复杂的
It turns out the previous generation, too, once had passionate and complicated
感情
feelings
也曾在人生的某个角落里
and once, in some corner of life
把不能说出的心意交给纸张
entrusted unspoken feelings to paper
那些书信被仔细保存下来
Those letters were carefully preserved
像时间深处的火种
like embers deep within time
鸠子带着这些信
Hatoko carried these letters with her.
前往伊豆大岛
She was headed for Izu Oshima.
汽船在海面行驶
The steamship sailed across the sea.
她在晃动中打盹
Rocked by the motion, she dozed off.
广播通知船将停靠冈田港
An announcement said the ship would soon dock at Okata Port.
她把装着书信的木盒放在腿上
She placed the wooden box holding the letters on her lap.
轻声对它们说
Softly, she spoke to them.
我们就快抵达伊豆大岛了
We’ll be arriving at Izu Oshima soon.
她相信那些信里的两个人
She believed the two people in those letters
是相爱的
had loved each other.
也许他们的爱安静
Perhaps their love was quiet.
也许激烈
Perhaps it was fierce.
也许被现实阻隔
Perhaps it was kept apart by reality.
也许从未得到普通意义上的圆满
Perhaps it had never found fulfillment in the ordinary sense.
但爱情本来就有各种形式
But love comes in many forms.
有些爱是一生相守
Some loves mean spending a lifetime together.
有些爱是相隔遥远仍然惦念
Some mean caring from far away, even across great distances.
有些爱适合在日光下被祝福
Some loves belong in the sunlight, blessed by others.
有些爱只能藏进抽屉
Some can only be hidden away in a drawer.
等多年后由另一个人轻轻打开
Years later, waiting for another person to gently open it.
船靠岸时
As the boat approached the shore
天空覆着厚厚的云层
the sky was blanketed in thick clouds
鸠子对那些书信说
Hatoko said to the letters,
你们很快就可以融为一体了
You will soon become one.
这样一句话
That single sentence
像为旧日情感举行的安静仪式
felt like a quiet ceremony for emotions from long ago.
她不是去揭开隐私
She was not there to expose anyone's secrets,
也不是去评判长辈的人生
nor to judge the lives of her elders,
而是以代笔人的温柔
but, with the tenderness of a ghostwriter,
把曾经被分开的心意送到该去的
to carry feelings that had once been separated to where they belonged,
地方
to their proper place.
书信在这里不再只是传递消息的
Here, letters were no longer merely a means
工具
of conveying messages.
它们有重量
They had weight,
有灵魂
they had souls,
甚至像沉睡的生命
and even seemed like sleeping lives.
鸠子一路护着木盒
Hatoko protected the wooden box all the way,
仿佛护着两颗迟到的心
as if guarding two hearts that had arrived too late.
抵达伊豆大岛后
After reaching Izu Oshima,
冬马先生来接她
Mr. Toma came to pick her up.
镰仓红茶店里的冬马先生和岛上
Mr. Toma in the Kamakura tea shop and
的冬马先生很不一样
Mr. Toma on the island seemed like two very different people.
此时他头发蓬乱
Now his hair was tousled,
带着野性的气息
and he carried a wild, untamed air,
像是被岛上的风和海重新塑造过
as if the island wind and sea had reshaped him.
两个人寒暄
The two of them exchanged pleasantries,
谈船
talked about boats,
谈海
talked about the sea,
也谈那项艰难的委托
and also about that difficult commission.
冬马先生希望鸠子替他写一封信
Mr. Toma hoped Hatoko would write a letter for him,
而这封信并不好写
but it was not an easy letter to write.
它不仅需要技巧
It required more than skill;
更需要代笔人真正触碰到一个人
it required the ghostwriter to truly touch
的孤独、纠结、愤怒和希望
a person's loneliness, conflict, anger, and hope.
鸠子一开始以为自己能够完成
At first, Hatoko thought she could do it.
可后来她发现
But later she realized
事情没有那么简单
it was not that simple.
优秀的代笔人不是把句子写得漂
A good ghostwriter is not someone who makes the sentences pret
亮
ty,
而是要让委托人的心准确地出现
but someone who lets the client's heart appear exactly as it is.
在纸上
On paper
若不能抵达那颗心
if they cannot reach that heart,
再华丽的文字也只是空壳
even the most ornate words are only an empty shell.
这个认知让鸠子陷入停滞
This realization brought Kyuko to a standstill.
四月来了
April arrived.
阳菜穿着略显肥大的新校服升入
Hina, in her slightly oversized new school uniform, moved on to
高中
high school.
小梅和莲太朗也开始读小学二年
Koume and Rentaro also began their second year of elementary
级
school.
海水依旧寒冷
The seawater was still cold,
蜜朗却频繁去海边冲浪
yet Mitsuro went to the beach to surf more and more often.
全家似乎都在向前
The whole family seemed to be moving forward.
只有鸠子停在原地
Only Kyuko remained stuck in place.
世界春光烂漫
The world was radiant with spring,
她却郁郁寡欢
but she was sunk in gloom.
樱花散尽
The cherry blossoms had all fallen,
绿叶满枝
and the branches were full of green leaves.
她才意识到自己可能已经燃烧殆
Only then did she realize she might have burned herself
尽
out.
上代的情书供养完毕
The previous generation's love letters had all been laid to rest.
阳菜也顺利升学
Hina also moved on to the next stage of school without a hitch.
眼前的大任务一个个结束
The big tasks before her were coming to an end, one by one.
空虚却随之到来
But emptiness soon followed.
人有时就是这样
People are like that sometimes.
忙的时候以为
When they're busy, they think
只要把所有事情完成
that once everything is done,
就会轻松
they'll finally feel at ease,
就会快乐
and finally be happy.
可真正停下来
But once they truly stop,
反而不知道自己为什么存在
they no longer know why they even exist.
那些被任务支撑的日子一旦结束
Once the days held up by tasks come to an end,
内心的空洞便显露出来
the emptiness inside begins to show.
鸠子不知道自己为了什么而活
Hatoko didn't know what she was living for.
仿佛沉进一片宽阔的泥沼
It was as if she were sinking into a vast swamp of mud,
连脖子都埋在里面
buried in it up to her neck.
她想靠工作摆脱这种情绪
She tried to escape those feelings through work,
可代笔工作也停滞不前
but her ghostwriting work had also stalled.
脑袋昏沉
Her mind felt foggy.
毫无干劲
She had no motivation at all.
想尝试新事物
She wanted to try something new.
又一动身就畏首畏尾
Yet the moment she sets out, she becomes timid and hesitant.
冬马先生的信迟迟没有动笔
Hatoko still hasn't been able to start Mr. Toma's letter.
她开始怀疑自己当初接下委托是
She begins to wonder whether accepting the commission in the first place
不是太自负
was an act of overconfidence.
那份羞愧很沉重
The shame weighs heavily on her,
因为它触及她最在意的地方
because it touches the thing she cares about most.
对鸠子来说
For Hatoko,
代笔不是普通工作
writing letters for others is not just an ordinary job.
而是她与世界连接的方式
It is her way of staying connected to the world.
如果她无法写信
If she cannot write letters,
仿佛也就无法确认自己是谁
it is as if she can no longer be sure who she is.
小川糸在这里写出了中年生活里
Here, Ito Ogawa captures a kind of exhaustion in middle age
不常被大声谈论的疲惫
that is not often spoken of openly.
不是灾难性的崩溃
It is not a catastrophic collapse,
而是慢慢失去力气
but a slow draining away of strength.
孩子长大了
The children have grown up.
家庭运行起来了
The household is running smoothly.
该完成的事完成了
Everything that needed doing has been done.
可自己却空了
And yet she herself feels hollowed out.
这个空并不代表不幸福
That emptiness does not mean she is unhappy.
也不代表不感恩
Nor does it mean you're ungrateful
恰恰因为生活表面看起来还不错
Precisely because life looks pretty good on the surface
人们才更难承认自己正在痛苦
it becomes even harder for people to admit they are in pain
鸠子的低落并没有被一句励志的
Jiuzi's low mood was not cured by some inspirational
话治好
line
她需要时间
She needs time
需要承认自己的无能为力
needs to acknowledge her own powerlessness
也需要重新学习如何不把价值完
and needs to relearn how not to place her entire sense of worth
全寄托在能否完成某件事上
on whether she can accomplish a certain thing
书里的温柔正在于此
This is where the book's tenderness lies
它不催促你振作
It doesn't rush you to pull yourself together
不要求你立刻变好
doesn't demand that you get better right away
而是陪你坐一会儿
but simply sits with you for a while
就像有人在夜里递给你一杯温热
like someone handing you a warm
的饮品
drink in the night
说
and saying
今天先到这里也可以
It's okay to stop here for today
明天不必一下子变得光明
Tomorrow doesn't have to become bright all at once
只要能醒来
as long as you can wake up
能洗脸
and wash your face
能打开窗
Being able to open the window
就已经是在往前
already means moving forward.
除了鸠子的个人困境
Beyond Hatoko's personal struggles,
书中也一直有家庭的细微流动
the book is also filled with subtle shifts within the family.
蜜朗并不是一个被写成完美伴侣
Mitsuro is not written as a perfect partner
的人
or person.
他有自己的节奏
He has his own rhythm,
有自己的沉默
his own silences.
有时与鸠子靠近
Sometimes he draws close to Hatoko,
有时又像隔着一层日常的雾
and sometimes he seems separated from her by a thin fog of everyday life.
但他们之间有共同生活后形成的
But between them there is something formed through living together:
温度
warmth.
一起放烟火
They set off fireworks together,
处理水桶里的余烬
deal with the embers left in the bucket,
在孩子的问题上试探着沟通
and tentatively communicate about the child.
在各自疲惫时保持某种不张扬的
When each of them is exhausted, they maintain a kind of understated
陪伴
companionship.
婚姻在书里不是浓烈告白
Marriage in the book is not a passionate confession,
而是许多小动作累积出来的关系
but a relationship built up through countless small gestures.
有人把剩下的红酒带回家
Someone brings the leftover red wine home.
有人深夜提前睡去也不必愧疚
No one needs to feel guilty for going to bed early late at night
有人用省略主语的句子说夏天结
Someone says, with the subject left out, that summer
束了
is over
另一个人听懂了
and the other person understands
这样的懂
That kind of understanding
平凡
is ordinary
却难得
yet rare
阳菜的成长线也很动人
Hina's coming-of-age arc is also deeply moving
她从那个被称作QP妹妹的小女
She goes from the little girl once called QP's kid sister
孩
that child
进入了不愿回应母亲的青春期
into adolescence, unwilling to answer her mother
她穿上新校服
She puts on her new school uniform
衣服还有些大
and it is still a little too big
像未来先一步披在身上
as if the future has settled on her shoulders first
而身体和心都还在适应
while her body and heart are still learning to adjust
父母看孩子长大
When parents watch their children grow up
常常有一种迟来的失落
there is often a belated sense of loss
明明一直盼着他们独立
They had clearly been hoping all along for them to become independent
盼着他们能照顾自己
hoping they could take care of themselves
可当那一天真的到来
but when that day truly arrives
又会怀念他们黏在身边的日子
you’ll miss the days when they were always glued to your side
鸠子对阳菜的感受
Kyuko's feelings for Hina
就是这种矛盾
It's exactly this kind of contradiction.
她想靠近
She wants to get closer
又必须后退
had to step back again
她想了解
She wants to know more.
又要尊重秘密
And you have to respect secrets.
她想帮忙
She wants to help.
却知道有些路孩子只能自己走
Yet they know there are some paths children have to walk on their own.
亲子之间最难的爱
The hardest kind of love between parent and child
不是紧紧抱住
It's not about holding on tightly.
而是在合适的时候松手
but letting go at the right time
并且让孩子知道
And let the child know
如果有一天她想回头
If one day she wants to turn back
家里的灯还亮着
The lights at home are still on
山茶文具店本身
The Camellia Stationery Shop itself
也是这部作品里安静而重要的存
It is also a quiet yet important presence in this work.
在
Here.
那是一间老店
That was an old shop.
连接着过去与现在
Connecting the past and the present
纸张、信封、笔墨、印章
Paper, envelopes, ink and brushes, seals
所有看似过时的东西
Everything that seems outdated
在这里都保有庄重的生命
Here, all life retains its solemn dignity.
现代人传递信息太快
People today share information too quickly.
快到连感情也常常变得仓促
So fast that even feelings often become rushed.
可写信需要坐下来
But writing a letter means you have to sit down.
需要选择纸
You need to select the paper.
需要考虑称呼
You need to consider how to address them.
需要一笔一画写下不能撤回的句
You need to write it down stroke by stroke—a sentence that can’t be taken back.
子
Child
它迫使人变慢
It forces people to slow down
也迫使人诚实
It also forces people to be honest.
代笔更是如此
This is even more true for ghostwriting.
鸠子要替别人写
Hatoko is going to write for someone else.
却不能把自己写进去太多
But you can't put too much of yourself into it.
她要理解委托人
She needs to understand her client.
却不能替对方做出情感判断
but they can't make emotional judgments on the other person's behalf
她要让信读起来自然
She wants the letter to read naturally.
像那个人亲手写下的一样
As if that person had written it by hand.
这样的工作要求极高的共情
This kind of work requires an exceptionally high level of empathy.
也要求极强的克制
It also demands extraordinary restraint
也许这正是《山茶的情书》适合
Perhaps this is exactly why Love Letter of Camellia is so well suited
睡前听的原因
to listening before sleep
它的核心并不是事件
At its heart, it is not about events
而是人与人之间那些没有说尽的
but about all the things left unsaid between people
话
the words
夜深的时候
Late at night
我们也会想起一些没有寄出的信
we, too, may think of letters we never sent
想起曾经应该道歉却没有道歉的
think of the people we should have apologized to but never did
人
the people
想起爱过却错过的人
think of those we loved but missed
想起已经离开的亲人
think of loved ones who have already gone
想起孩子小时候的样子
think of what our children looked like when they were small
想起某个再也回不去的季节
think of a season we can never return to
我们可能不会真的拿起笔
We may never actually pick up a pen
但故事提醒我们
but the story reminds us
那些心意并没有完全消失
that those feelings have not completely disappeared
它们只是沉到更深的地方
They have only sunk to a deeper place
等待某个安静的时刻
waiting for some quiet moment
被温柔地看见
to be seen with tenderness
小川糸的文字里
In Ito Ogawa's writing
食物和季节总是承担着疗愈的力
food and the seasons always carry a healing power
量
a measure of it
樱花、紫阳花、金木樨、山茶、
Cherry blossoms, hydrangeas, osmanthus, camellias,
明日叶、莲
ashitaba, lotus
这些章节名像一串植物的名字
these chapter titles read like a string of plant names
也像时间在土地上留下的标记
and also like marks left by time upon the land
春天的樱花告诉人们重新开始
Spring's cherry blossoms tell people to begin again
夏末的线香花火让人承认结束
late-summer sparklers ask us to accept an ending
秋天的金木樨以香气唤醒记忆
autumn's osmanthus awakens memory with its fragrance
冬天的山茶在寒冷中开花
winter's camellias bloom in the cold
明日叶带着明天仍会长出的意味
ashitaba carries the sense that tomorrow it will grow again
莲则从泥中伸展
while the lotus rises from the mud
安静地开出清洁的花
quietly opening into a pure flower
植物不会解释人生
Plants do not explain life
却用生长和凋谢陪伴人类
yet through growth and withering, they keep us company
它们让我们知道
They let us know
低落不是永恒
that sadness is not eternal
盛放也不会永远停留
and even full bloom will not linger forever
所有季节都会过去
Every season will pass
但过去并不等于失去
But the past is not the same as loss
它们会变成气味
They turn into scents
变成信纸上的字
into words on letter paper
变成某一天忽然想起时胸口的温
into the warmth in your chest when, one day, you suddenly remember
热
warmth
读这本书
Reading this book
也是在读鸠子对女性身份的重新
is also reading Hatoko's reworking of her identity as a woman
整理
a reordering
她不是只作为母亲而存在
She does not exist only as a mother
也不是只作为代笔人而存在
nor only as a ghostwriter
她会爱孩子
She loves her child
也会厌倦家务
and also grows tired of housework
她会珍惜家庭
She cherishes her family
也会怀念独处
and also misses being alone
她能替别人写出细腻的信
She can write delicate letters for others
却也会在自己的生活里语塞
yet in her own life, she can be at a loss for words
她温柔
She is gentle
却并不总是从容
but not always composed
这样的不完美让她可信
That imperfection makes her believable
很多时候
Much of the time
我们也像鸠子一样
We are much like Hatoko, too
在别人眼里已经做得很好
seen by others as already doing so well
却在心里暗暗觉得自己不够好
yet quietly feeling inside that we are not good enough
我们承担了许多
We carry so much
却仍然怀疑自己是否有价值
and still wonder whether we have any worth
我们照顾别人太久
We have spent so long caring for others
反而忘了怎样照顾自己
that we have forgotten how to care for ourselves
《山茶的情书》没有把鸠子塑造
The Camellia Letter does not portray Hatoko
成永远给予的人
as someone who gives endlessly
而是让她疲惫
Instead, it lets her be exhausted
让她停下
lets her stop
让她承认写不出来
lets her admit she cannot write
正因为如此
And precisely because of that
当她后来一点点恢复
when she later begins to recover, little by little
我们才会相信那不是奇迹
we believe it is not a miracle
而是人真实的复原
but a real human healing
复原从来不是一条直线
Recovery is never a straight line
它可能是某天愿意出门
It might be being willing to go out one day
某天能认真吃饭
being able to eat a proper meal one day
某天终于回了一封消息
or finally replying to a message one day
某天忽然发现自己又能分辨风里
One day, you suddenly realize you can once again make out, in the wind,
的花香
the scent of flowers.
故事中的旧信供养
The offering of old letters in the story
也有一种很东方的哀悼感
also carries a very Eastern sense of mourning.
供养不是销毁
Offering them up is not destruction,
而是让无法抵达的心意获得安息
but a way to let feelings that could never arrive find peace.
那些信曾经承载爱、思念、秘密
Those letters once held love, longing, secrets,
和岁月
and the passage of years.
如今被送往终点
Now they are being sent to their final destination,
并不是为了抹去
not in order to erase them,
而是为了让它们不再孤单
but so they no longer have to be alone.
鸠子对木盒说话的场景尤其温柔
The scene where Hatoko speaks to the wooden box is especially gentle.
她把信当成有生命的存在
She treats the letters as living beings,
相信它们也期待重逢
believing that they, too, are waiting to be reunited.
这样的想象并不幼稚
This kind of imagining is not childish.
人类之所以需要仪式
The reason humans need rituals
正是因为有些情感无法用道理处
is precisely because some emotions cannot be dealt with by reason
理
alone.
告别需要动作
Farewell needs an action.
思念需要容器
Longing needs a vessel.
爱需要被安放
Love needs a place to rest.
信纸是容器
Letter paper is a vessel
火焰是容器
The flame is a vessel.
旅程也是容器
The journey is also a vessel
鸠子把这些容器一一准备好
Jiuzi prepared each of these containers one by one
替上一代人完成迟来的拥抱
Giving the previous generation the belated embrace they never had
也正是在这个过程中
And it was precisely during this process
她重新理解了上代
She came to understand the previous generation in a new way.
那个曾经严厉得让她受伤的祖母
the grandmother whose strictness had once hurt her
也曾是会爱、会痛、会隐藏秘密
They, too, once knew how to love, how to hurt, and how to hide secrets.
的女人
the woman
当长辈从权威变成一个具体的人
When an elder goes from being an authority figure to a real, specific person
和解才真正开始
Only then does reconciliation truly begin.
我们很多人都要到长大后
Many of us don’t realize it until we grow up
甚至到对方离开后
Even after the other person has left
才慢慢看见父母或祖父母的人生
only gradually come to see the lives of our parents or grandparents
他们不是天生的长辈
They weren’t born as elders.
他们也曾年轻
They were young once, too
也曾笨拙
I was once awkward too
也曾在深夜里不知如何是好
There were times late at night when I didn’t know what to do
看见这一点
Seeing this
并不会让过去的伤自动消失
doesn't make the wounds of the past disappear on their own
却会让心里的硬块稍微松动
but it does loosen the hard knot in the heart a little
鸠子的成长
Hatoko's growth
不是变得更强势
is not about becoming more forceful
而是变得更能容纳复杂
but about becoming more able to hold complexity
她开始明白
She begins to understand
一个人可以既伤害过你
that someone can have hurt you
也爱过你
and also loved you
一段感情可以没有结果
A relationship can lead nowhere
却仍然真实
and still have been real
一封信可以迟到很多年
A letter can arrive many years late
却依然值得被送达
and still be worth delivering
听到这里
Hearing this
也许你会发现
you may find
《山茶的情书》写的是代笔屋
that The Love Letter of Camellia is about a letter-writing shop
其实也是在写语言的边界
but it is also about the limits of language
语言很重要
Language matters deeply
却不是万能
but it is not all-powerful
鸠子擅长写信
Hatoko is good at writing letters
可她无法立刻解决阳菜的青春期
But she couldn't immediately resolve Hina's adolescence.
无法马上驱散自己的空虚
She couldn't instantly dispel her own emptiness.
也无法轻易写出冬马先生的心
Nor could she easily write Mr. Toma's heart onto the page.
真正珍贵的语言
Truly precious words
不是随时都有
are not always at hand.
而是在沉默足够久之后
They are the one sentence that finally appears
终于出现的那一句
after silence has lasted long enough.
我们常常急着表达
We are often in a hurry to express ourselves,
急着解释
in a hurry to explain,
急着证明自己没有错
in a hurry to prove we weren't wrong.
可有些话需要等待
But some words need to wait.
等待情绪沉淀
Wait for emotions to settle,
等待理解加深
wait for understanding to deepen,
等待自己有能力承担说出口之后
wait until we are capable of bearing
的重量
the weight of saying them aloud.
鸠子迟迟没有写冬马先生的信
Hatoko's long delay in writing Mr. Toma's letter
表面看是失败
may look like failure on the surface.
实际上是她对文字的敬畏
But in truth, it is her reverence for words.
她不愿用漂亮话敷衍别人的人生
She refuses to gloss over someone else's life with pretty phrases.
这样的停顿
A pause like this
也是一种诚实
It is also a kind of honesty
睡前听这本书
Listening to this book before bed
最适合把注意力放在那些小小的
is perfect for placing your attention on those tiny
声音上
sounds
线香花火落地时的轻响
the soft tap of a sparkler falling to the ground
水桶里的水晃动的声音
the sound of water sloshing in a bucket
热红酒在锅里微微冒泡的声音
the quiet bubbling of mulled wine in a pot
汽船靠岸前发动机变慢的声音
the sound of a steamboat's engine slowing before it docks
老屋里夜晚的风声
the night wind in an old house
纸张被铺开的声音
the sound of paper being spread out
这些声音并不喧哗
These sounds are not loud
却把生活一层层托住
yet they hold up life, layer by layer
我们的一天也许很乱
Our days may be chaotic
消息很多
with so many messages
任务很多
so many tasks
情绪来不及整理
and emotions we have no time to sort through
但当故事慢下来
But when the story slows down
我们也跟着慢下来
we slow down with it
你可以想象自己坐在山茶文具店
You can imagine yourself sitting in a corner
的一角
of the Camellia Stationery Shop
面前有一张信纸
There is a sheet of stationery in front of you
一支好写的笔
and a pen that writes smoothly.
你不必立刻写出完整的信
You don’t have to write a complete letter right away.
只要想一想
Just think for a moment:
如果今晚要给某个人写一句话
if you were to write one sentence to someone tonight,
你会写给谁
who would you write it to?
也许是给远方的朋友
Maybe to a friend far away,
告诉对方你其实一直记得
telling them you’ve actually remembered them all along.
也许是给亲人
Maybe to a family member,
说有些感谢从来没好好讲过
saying there are some thanks you never properly expressed.
也许是给曾经的爱人
Maybe to someone you once loved,
说祝你平安
saying, I wish you peace.
也许是给小时候的自己
Maybe to your childhood self,
说你已经很努力了
saying, you’ve already worked so hard.
也许
Or maybe
是给现在的自己
it’s to the person you are now.
很多人最不会写的
The letter many people find hardest to write
就是给自己的信
is the one addressed to themselves.
我们对别人可以温柔
We can be gentle with others,
对自己却常常苛刻
yet we are often harsh with ourselves.
鸠子的故事提醒我们
Hatoko's story reminds us
也要把自己当成值得被代笔、被
that we, too, should see ourselves as people worthy of having our words written for us, of being
倾听、被认真安放的人
heard, and of being held with care
如果你最近也像鸠子一样
If lately you, like Hatoko,
觉得自己停在原地
feel as though you're standing still
而周围的人都在往前走
while everyone around you is moving forward,
请不要太责备自己
please don't be too hard on yourself.
生命并不是每个季节都必须开花
Life doesn't have to bloom in every season.
有时候
Sometimes,
根在土里修复
the roots are healing underground,
外面看不见动静
with no visible movement on the surface.
山茶在冷天开放
Camellias bloom in the cold.
莲从泥里长出
Lotuses rise from the mud.
明日叶被摘下后仍会在明天生出
Ashitaba, even after being picked, will sprout again tomorrow
新芽
with new shoots.
植物从不因为暂时沉默就怀疑自
Plants never doubt themselves just because they are silent for a while
己
themselves.
人也可以如此
People can be like that too.
你可以有低潮
You are allowed to have low periods.
可以写不出来
You are allowed to be unable to write.
可以不想说话
It's okay not to feel like talking
可以在完成一件大事之后突然空
It's okay to suddenly feel empty after accomplishing something big
下来
to come down from it
这些都不是失败
None of this is failure
而是身心在提醒你
It's your body and mind reminding you
需要重新分配力气
that you need to redistribute your strength
请允许自己慢一点
Please allow yourself to slow down a little
真正的恢复
True recovery
不是回到过去那个完美运转的自
is not about returning to that perfectly functioning self
己
you once were
而是在新的生活里
but about finding, within a new life,
找到新的呼吸方式
a new way to breathe
《山茶的情书》最动人的地方
Perhaps the most moving thing about Love Letters of Camellia
也许就在它不追求彻底的解决
is that it does not chase a complete resolution
阳菜还会继续长大
Hina will keep growing up
鸠子还会继续摸索
Hatoko will keep feeling her way forward
代笔屋还会迎来新的委托
the letter-writing shop will keep receiving new commissions
旧屋的冬天仍旧寒冷
the old house will still be cold in winter
热红酒也许还会在某个夜晚被煮
and mulled wine may yet be simmered on some night
起
once again
生活不会因为一本书的结束就变
Life doesn't become tidy just because a book comes to an end.
得整齐
and neatly ordered.
可我们听完之后
But after listening,
心里会多一点柔软的耐心
our hearts gain a little more gentle patience.
我们知道
We come to understand
人与人之间的关系可以慢慢修补
that relationships between people can be mended slowly.
迟到的心意仍然有机会被理解
Belated feelings can still find a chance to be understood.
沉默的季节也有它的意义
Even seasons of silence have their meaning.
山茶花开的时候
When the camellias bloom,
并不热闹
there is no fanfare.
它在寒风里保持自己的红
They keep their own red alive in the cold wind,
像一封没有大声朗读的情书
like a love letter never read aloud.
它告诉我们
They tell us
爱不一定总是汹涌
that love doesn't always have to be overwhelming.
也可以是克制的守候
It can also be a restrained kind of waiting.
陪伴不一定总在身边
Companionship doesn't always have to be by your side.
也可以藏在一张纸、一句话、一
It can also be tucked inside a sheet of paper, a single sentence, or a
段被记住的时光里
stretch of time that someone remembers.
今晚的故事就让它停在这里吧
Let's let tonight's story stop here.
请把那些尚未说出口的话
Please keep those words you have yet to say
暂时放在心里最安全的地方
Keep it for now in the safest place in your heart
也许明天醒来
Maybe when you wake up tomorrow
你会愿意写下一句
you’ll be willing to write the next line
也许还不会
or maybe not yet
那也没有关系
and that’s okay too
信可以慢慢写
A letter can be written slowly
人生也可以慢慢过
and life can be lived slowly too
愿你在这个夜晚被温柔包围
May you be wrapped in tenderness tonight
愿你心里那些没有寄出的信
May all the letters in your heart that were never sent
都有一天找到安放之处
one day find a place to rest
愿你像山茶一样
May you be like a camellia
在寒冷里也保有颜色
keeping your color even in the cold
像明日叶一样
like ashitaba
相信明天还会长出新的叶子
believing new leaves will grow again tomorrow
也像鸠子一样
and like Hatoko too
即使一度停下
even if you once came to a stop
也终会在自己的节奏里
you will, in your own rhythm,
重新铺开信纸
unfold the letter paper once more
写下属于生活的下一行
and write the next line that belongs to life
温柔解读小川糸《山茶的情书》
A gentle reading of Ito Ogawa’s The Camellia Love Letter
从山茶文具店重新开门
From the reopening of the Camellia Stationery Shop
到家人、旧信、离别与自我修复
to family, old letters, farewells, and self-healing
在镰仓四季的光影里
in the shifting light of Kamakura’s four seasons
陪你慢慢听见生活深处的回声
we’ll help you slowly hear the echoes deep within everyday life
适合睡前、通勤、独处时安静收
perfect for quiet listening before bed, on your commute, or when you’re alone
听
listen
这一段可以作为旁白的延展：从
This section can serve as an extension of the narration: starting from
人物处境进入主题
the characters’ circumstances and moving into the theme
再回到读者自身的经验
then returning to the reader’s own experiences
让内容更完整
to make the content feel more complete
也更适合三十分钟听书视频的节
and better suited to the pacing of a thirty-minute audiobook video
奏
rhythm
温柔解读小川糸《山茶的情书》
A gentle reading of Ito Ogawa’s The Letters of Camellia
从山茶文具店重新开门
From the reopening of the Camellia Stationery Shop
到家人、旧信、离别与自我修复
to family, old letters, farewells, and self-healing
在镰仓四季的光影里
in the shifting light of Kamakura’s four seasons
陪你慢慢听见生活深处的回声
we’ll help you slowly hear the echoes deep within everyday life
适合睡前、通勤、独处时安静收
perfect for quiet listening before bed, on your commute, or when you’re alone
听
listen
这一段可以作为旁白的延展：从
This section can serve as an extension of the narration: starting from
人物处境进入主题
The characters' circumstances bring us into the theme
再回到读者自身的经验
then lead us back to the reader's own experience
让内容更完整
making the content feel more complete
也更适合三十分钟听书视频的节
and better suited to the pacing of a thirty-minute audiobook video
奏
rhythm
温柔解读小川糸《山茶的情书》
A gentle reading of Ito Ogawa's Camellia Letters
从山茶文具店重新开门
from the reopening of the Camellia Stationery Store
到家人、旧信、离别与自我修复
to family, old letters, farewells, and self-healing
在镰仓四季的光影里
amid the changing light and shadows of Kamakura's four seasons
陪你慢慢听见生活深处的回声
accompanying you as you slowly hear the echoes deep within everyday life
适合睡前、通勤、独处时安静收
perfect for quiet listening before bed, on your commute, or when you're alone
听
listen
这一段可以作为旁白的延展：从
This section can serve as an extended voiceover: from
人物处境进入主题
the characters' circumstances bringing us into the theme
再回到读者自身的经验
then leading us back to the reader's own experience
让内容更完整
making the content feel more complete
也更适合三十分钟听书视频的节
and better suited to the pacing of a thirty-minute audiobook video
奏
rhythm
温柔解读小川糸《山茶的情书》
A gentle reading of Ito Ogawa's Camellia Letters
从山茶文具店重新开门
from the reopening of the Camellia Stationery Store
到家人、旧信、离别与自我修复
to family, old letters, farewells, and self-healing
在镰仓四季的光影里
In the shifting light of Kamakura through the seasons
陪你慢慢听见生活深处的回声
Letting you slowly hear the echoes deep within everyday life
适合睡前、通勤、独处时安静收
Perfect for quiet listening before bed, on your commute, or when you're alone
听
listen
这一段可以作为旁白的延展：从
This section can serve as an extension of the narration: moving from
人物处境进入主题
the characters' circumstances into the main theme
再回到读者自身的经验
then returning to the reader's own experience
让内容更完整
making the content feel more complete
也更适合三十分钟听书视频的节
and better suited to the pacing of a thirty-minute audiobook video
奏
rhythm
温柔解读小川糸《山茶的情书》
A gentle reading of Ito Ogawa's The Camellia Letters
从山茶文具店重新开门
From the reopening of the Camellia Stationery Shop
到家人、旧信、离别与自我修复
to family, old letters, farewells, and self-healing
在镰仓四季的光影里
In the shifting light of Kamakura through the seasons
陪你慢慢听见生活深处的回声
Letting you slowly hear the echoes deep within everyday life
适合睡前、通勤、独处时安静收
Perfect for quiet listening before bed, on your commute, or when you're alone
听
listen
这一段可以作为旁白的延展：从
This section can serve as an extension of the narration: moving from
人物处境进入主题
the characters' circumstances into the main theme
再回到读者自身的经验
then return to the reader’s own experience
让内容更完整
to make the content feel more complete
也更适合三十分钟听书视频的节
and better suited to the pacing of a thirty-minute audiobook video
奏
rhythm
温柔解读小川糸《山茶的情书》
A gentle reading of Ito Ogawa’s Tsubaki Stationery Store
从山茶文具店重新开门
from the reopening of the Tsubaki Stationery Store
到家人、旧信、离别与自我修复
to family, old letters, farewells, and self-healing
在镰仓四季的光影里
amid the changing light and shadows of Kamakura’s four seasons
陪你慢慢听见生活深处的回声
guiding you to slowly hear the echoes deep within everyday life
适合睡前、通勤、独处时安静收
perfect for quiet listening before bed, on your commute, or when you’re alone
听
listening
这一段可以作为旁白的延展：从
This section can serve as an expanded voiceover: moving from
人物处境进入主题
the characters’ circumstances into the central themes
再回到读者自身的经验
then returning to the reader’s own experience
让内容更完整
to make the content feel more complete
也更适合三十分钟听书视频的节
and better suited to the pacing of a thirty-minute audiobook video
奏
rhythm